<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ananthan Ambikairajah</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ananthan Ambikairajah</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Plagiarism - what does it mean?</title>
      <link>/post/190508-self-plagiarism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/190508-self-plagiarism/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;plagiarism.jpg&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always thought that plagiarism was a relatively easy concept to understand. In short, if you copied someone else’s work or ideas without sufficient credit, then you were likely to be guilty of plagiarism. It wasn’t until I entered academia that I began to question the meaning of plagiarism. Particularly the idea of self-plagiarism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you plagiarise yourself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One clear example in academia is to publish the exact same paper in two (or more) different journals. However, almost all journals require authors to sign a statement which declares that their manuscript has not been submitted for publication elsewhere. So this kind of self-plagiarism is usually rare and can be quickly caught out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After considering this example, the question becomes, what/where is the line for reusing one’s own work? For example, often in science the same methodology can be used to investigate different questions. At what point is self-plagiarism an issue in this sense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anecdotal evidence that I have gathered from colleagues is mixed. Some say that there is no need to change the methodology if the approach is appropriate for the question. Others believe that whilst you theoretically should not need to change the methodology, practically, rewording everything will save you some grief with journals. I have previously had a manuscript rejected by a journal because of this issue, with the journal citing “your manuscript provides less new information than is expected from our readership…unfortunately we cannot proceed with your manuscript because of the significant overlap with your previously published paper”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real underlying issue with this form of self-plagiarism is copyright, given that the journals own the copy-edited and typesetted version of the manuscript. Therefore, the journal that you choose to submit to does not want to be liable for copyright infringement and as a result, would rather turn away articles that use similar methodology/formatting than deal with the associated issues of publishing such manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although, I wonder whether this process is doing more harm than good. These problems may represent a larger issue in science regarding the negative stigma surrounding replication. There is a constant push to do new things such that the value of established ideas or even null-results can get lost in the process. If the purpose of scientific inquiry is to explain and understand phenomena, then isn’t replication an integral part of this process?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final question is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why reinvent the wheel if you were the one who invented it in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fat mass changes during menopause: a meta-analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/20190426_fat-mass-and-menopause-meta-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/20190426_fat-mass-and-menopause-meta-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt; Fat mass has been shown to increase in ageing women, however, the extent to which menopausal status mediates these changes remains unclear.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Objectives:&lt;/strong&gt; To determine (i) how fat mass differs in quantity and distribution between premenopausal and postmenopausal women, (ii) whether and how age and/or menopausal status moderates any observed differences and (iii) which type of fat mass measure is best suited to detecting differences in fat mass between groups.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Study Design:&lt;/strong&gt; This review with meta-analysis is reported according to MOOSE guidelines.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Data sources and populations:&lt;/strong&gt; Studies (published up to May 2018) were identified via PubMed to provide fat mass measures in premenopausal and postmenopausal women. 201 cross-sectional studies were included in the meta-analysis, which provided a combined sample size of 1 049 919 individuals consisting of 478 734 premenopausal women and 571 185 postmenopausal women. 11 longitudinal studies were included in the meta-analyses, which provided a combined sample size of 2 472 women who were premenopausal at baseline and postmenopausal at follow up.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; The main findings of this review were that fat mass significantly increased between premenopausal and postmenopausal women across most measures, including body mass index (1.14 kg/m2, 95 % confidence interval 0.95 to 1.32), body weight (1 kg, 0.44 to 1.57), body fat percentage (2.88 %, 2.13 to 3.63), waist circumference (4.63 cm, 3.90 to 5.35), hip circumference (2.01 cm, 1.36 to 2.65), waist to hip ratio (0.04, 0.03 to 0.05), visceral fat (26.90 cm2, 13.12 to 40.68) and trunk fat percentage (5.49 %, 3.91 to 7.06), with the exception of total leg fat percentage, which significantly decreased (-3.19 %, -5.98 to -0.41). No interactive effects were observed between menopausal status and age across all fat mass measures.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; The change in fat mass quantity between premenopausal and postmenopausal women was predominantly attributable to increasing age with menopause having no significant additional influence. However, the decrease in total leg fat percentage and increase in measures of central fat are indicative of a possible change in fat mass distribution after menopause. These changes are likely to, at least in part, be due to hormonal shifts that occur during midlife with women having a higher androgen (i.e. testosterone) to estradiol ratio after menopause, which has been linked to enhanced central adiposity deposition. Evidently, these findings suggest attention should be paid to the accumulation of central fat after menopause, whereas increases in total fat mass should be monitored consistently across the lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ambikairajah, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, Walsh, E., Tabatabaei-Jafari, H., &amp;amp; Cherbuin, N. (2019). Fat mass changes during menopause: a meta-analysis. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Journal of Obstetrics &amp;amp; Gynecology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Accepted in Press&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajog.2019.04.023&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.ajog.2019.04.023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>E-Examinations and the Student Experience Regarding Appropriateness of Assessment and Course Quality in Science and Medical Science</title>
      <link>/publication/20190107_e-exams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/20190107_e-exams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest in, and use of, computers and software for assessment is reported to be increasingly popular via electronic examinations (e-exams). We deepen our understanding of the design, reception, and effectiveness of e-exams for history and philosophy of science modules, undertaken by first-year advanced science and medical science students at university. We employ a quasi-experimental research design approach to examine our implementation of e-exams on reported student satisfaction regarding the suitability of the information provided about the assessment requirements, appropriateness of the assessment methods, and overall quality of the associated courses. We report statistically significant increases in student satisfaction regarding the suitability and appropriateness of the assessment methods or requirements. The outcomes of this research highlight new avenues for educators to explore including (a) the innovative use of associated software (Maple TA™) for e-exams and (b) the implications that e-exams can have on the student experience in the context of medium-stakes testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ambikairajah, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Tisdell, C. C. (2019). E-Examinations and the Student Experience Regarding Appropriateness of Assessment and Course Quality in Science and Medical Science. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Educational Technology Systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 47(4): 460-478. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/0047239518822016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;doi:10.&lt;sup&gt;1177&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;0047239518822016&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sci-Hub: A response to the scientific paywall</title>
      <link>/post/180907-sci-hub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/180907-sci-hub/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;sci-hub.jpg&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being involved in science enables the development of critical thinking skills, which ultimately helps you view the world through a different lens. The most powerful way to achieve this perspective is by questioning one step further using a simple word – “why?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, one question that has always puzzled me has been the commercialisation of water – Why do people pay for bottle water? Given that Australia’s water treatment process is of a high standard, I find it difficult to justify the cost of a resource that is readily available via tap. Perhaps there has been a generational effect, where the water quality in previous decades has not been to the standard seen currently, resulting in public skepticism. Alternatively, the behaviours we see today could be the result of incredibly smart marketing strategies, which have created the perception that water is better from a bottle and that consumers are paying the price for the quality of the water, instead of the more likely reason of packaging costs (Note: There may be other reasons here that I am overlooking. If you pay for bottled water, I’d be interested in hearing about your reasoning for doing so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for this slight tangent is because over the past few months I have been conducting a systematic review for my PhD, which has resulted in me reading close to 600 papers. During this process, I have had to retrieve a large number of articles from online journals, much of which was obtained through the universities’ proxy due to a paywall. You see, certain journals require a fee to view their articles, so instead of academics paying for this, universities spend a large amount of money to cover the access fees. If your university doesn’t have the article you are looking for, there are usually request forms for interlibrary loans that can be filled out which enable the librarians at the university to source the required article for you. Therefore, any staff or student associated with a university can reap the benefits of this service. This is all well and good for people associated with a university, but what about the public? The academic paywall appears to disadvantage eager learners who want to access journal papers but may not necessarily be attached to a university institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, lately I have found myself questioning, “why is this paywall even here in the first place?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers do not get paid by the journals to publish their articles. In fact, some researchers will be required to pay the journal to get their article considered and reviewed. The next logical assumption is that the journal pays the reviewers, however, this is not the case either. Reviewers are generally experts in the field and engage in the reviewing process for a number of reasons, some of which include a feeling of responsibility to give back to the scientific community, or in fact a deep interest in reading emerging research. Even editing positions within a journal are not all paid roles.&lt;br /&gt;
So where does the money go?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When reading the submission guidelines on journal websites, the general/vague reason provided is that the fee covers the cost of processing the article. Some journals even provide authors with a choice of paying the journals to ensure that their article is freely available, or submitting under an alternative model whereby the author does not pay the journal and these fees are passed on to people who are interested in the research, via a pay wall. Since we live in the digital age of science, most papers are published online, so I am currently scratching my head at what the current publishing costs involve, or whether the costs are justified at the current prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can be done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a push for authors to publish in open access journals, which has been moderately successful. However, for better or worse we live in a scientific community where metrics matter (such as impact factors) and not all high impact journals are open access, which could be a deterrent for some scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has also been a response to the publishing paywall, which has been through the creation of Sci-Hub by Alexandra Elbakyan. As a neuroscientist and computer programmer, Alexandra was frustrated with the lack of open access to scientific information. As a result, Sci-Hub is a website, which bypasses publisher paywalls by allowing access through educational institution proxies. The legality of the service is questionable with publishers engaging in countless lawsuits against the site and Alexandra herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does the future of science look like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future does look positive for the scientific community. With international targets such as Open Access by 2020, there is increasing recognition for the urgent need to disseminate all scientific findings to everyone and for journals to be accountable and transparently declare the costs behind their dissemination. Overall, hopefully this push for open access will encourage all citizens to become lifelong learners and furthermore, enable scientists to push the envelope further for society and make a larger positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women in science - what responsibility do male scientists have?</title>
      <link>/post/180817-women-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/180817-women-in-science/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;drkarl.jpeg&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National Science Week is drawing to a close and last night I had the pleasure of watching Professor Veena Sahajwalla from the University of New South Wales (UNSW), Sydney and Dr Karl Kruszelnicki from the University of Sydney (USyd), give extremely passionate and engaging talks at the National Convention Centre in Canberra. Topics were diverse and ranged from explaining current and future electronic waste recycling strategies to discussing the importance of understanding why diet alcoholic drinks get you drunk quicker. However, it was the first question asked by a young girl during Q&amp;amp;A, which I felt spoke volumes to a core theme of science week this year, which was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do we get more women into science?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more that I have thought about this question in the past, the more I have realised my own ignorance on the topic. When I was a fresh-faced undergraduate neuroscience student, I looked around the auditorium during lectures expecting to see a disparity in male to female student numbers. Surprisingly, in all of my lectures I saw equal, if not more women sitting in the lecture theatres with me. When volunteering with a wide range of neuroscience/psychology lab groups, once again I saw a similar trend, where the number of women significantly outweighed the number of men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was going on here? There has always been a strong push to promote the number of women in science and yet at every turn in my career I have not seen any shortage of women in science. Is it possible that neuroscience is ahead of its time in promoting gender equality in science? Perhaps getting women involved in science is a generational issue that has since been resolved by the fortitude and passion of senior female scientists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took this anecdotal evidence to my sister, Raji Ambikairajah – who is a passionate advocate for women in STEM careers. Surprisingly, my findings did not come as a shock to her in the slightest. She asked me one simple question, which enabled me to glimpse into the challenges that women face in STEM careers. The question was this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How many women were in the management roles within the research groups?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few quick moments, the realisation hit me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidently the increasing number of women in science today is not a reflection that the glass ceiling has been broken, instead it is an indication that the glass ceiling has been moved higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Determined to learn more, I looked to female leaders in STEM, which led me to find Sheryl Sandberg’s book “Lean In”. Sheryl Sandberg was the Vice President of global online sales and operations at Google before moving into the role of Chief Operating Officer for a small tech start up company that was working on providing a social media platform to connect people from all over the world. That social media platform was Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sandberg’s book provided further insight into the systemic challenges that women face in leadership and at the intersection between their professional and personal lives. This book led me to question the responsibility of male scientists to help promote gender equity in all levels of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being aware of this bias could be useful in providing some form of self-correction. This point has been emphasised by Sheryl Sandberg who says, “we cannot change what we are not aware of, and once we are aware, we cannot help but change”. As a result, awareness can ensure that more men support talented female researchers who are seeking to apply for executive roles. This is a critical strategy as it ensures that women can shape important decisions, which impact the future culture of scientific organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, in recent months there have been movements by prominent male scientists to take a stance and step down from conferences that did not include leading female scientists as well. This strategy has mostly been received well on social media; however, I am unsure whether this has resulted in the desired outcome or whether conference organisers just offer the position to another male scientist? Using this platform to raise awareness about the issue could be another way forward for male scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, the immense push by universities and other scientific organisations engaged in outreach has been an effective strategy for applying pressure to the social constructs within the scientific field. In saying this, it is always important to establish a marker for success when aiming to achieve a desired outcome. Whilst there are many measures to use for this issue, an important one for me is the normalisation of female scientists in leadership positions. To get to this place, however, a lot more work needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was taught that the way of progress was neither swift nor easy”&lt;br /&gt;
- Marie Curie&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should scientists engage with the public?</title>
      <link>/post/180803-science-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/180803-science-communication/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;science-communication.jpg&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words are incredible. Words can be used to express ideas, comfort others, inspire movements to spark change, create music that can unite people from different cultures…the list goes on. Equally so, however, words can be used to spread misinformation, cause confusion that leads to conflict and distrust, especially when taken out of context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering why I am talking about words when the title of this article is about scientists and public engagement? Simply put, scientists are in the “words business”. All year round, we are writing papers to summarise and disseminate our findings to the rest of the scientific community in addition to writing grant applications to fund our research. One important thing to note here is that a science career can be sustained (very successfully) through these two activities alone. As a result, science communication is a choice. Evidently, a choice that some scientists are hesitant to make - but why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant applications and research papers are structured pieces of writing, which are grounded within the scientific method. It is a very different style of thinking and communicating compared to engaging with the public. Since not all scientists are trained in communicating effectively to others outside of their field, the resulting effect is the oversimplification and sensationalisation of scientific messages due to external manipulation of the messaging. As a result, it can be argued that the credibility of science has been negatively impacted by the poor science communication that is prevalent in society. Don’t believe me? Ok, answer the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is wine good for you, or bad for you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do video games make children violent?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does &lt;strong&gt;insert any example here&lt;/strong&gt; cause cancer or help you live longer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear here. The issue is not that there are contrary findings present on each of these topics. In fact, if you search almost any topic in science you will find it rare to obtain a consensus on any issue. Whilst data never lies, it is our interpretation and explanation of data/trends, which can result in conflicting views. This is why we have the scientific method, which helps us remove our biases (as much as possible), test our theories and develop lines of evidence which hopefully converge to create widely held scientific models about the world. These scientific models, however, are always susceptible to change with emerging evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, a key issue is that scientific findings can be oversimplified or sensationalized to the public, resulting in unnecessary confusion. This can be a deterrent for scientists to commit the time and effort to disseminate their work to the public, when the mantra of “publish or perish” is very real in today’s academic culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst science communication is a choice, I hope that it is a choice that more scientists make. A possible solution is to not only state our findings, but also explain our justification and reasoning to the public. Secondly, the implementation of a curriculum within schools that can foster critical thinking amongst students is a key tool for winning the war on misinformation. Since the educational curriculum is a slow changing machine, this means that more scientists needs to be engaging with their local schools to help develop extracurricular programs or experiences for those students that help develop their fundamental critical thinking skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that there is an incredible thirst and desire for scientific knowledge amongst the public, which can be seen through the interest in the work that scientists such as Emma Johnston, Muireann Irish, Michelle Simmons and have conducted. As a result, I believe that there is an increasing responsibility for scientists to make an impact and engage with the community so that poor quality or misrepresented science is quickly identified, questioned and evaluated during public discourse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t follow your passions. Foster them</title>
      <link>/post/180727-dont-follow-your-passions-foster-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/180727-dont-follow-your-passions-foster-them/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;report_card.jpg&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I teach students, I take the same level of responsibility, care and commitment towards their learning and development as I would hope another teacher would show my future children. This can, at times, be emotionally arduous, when such a heavy investment is put into relationships that are inherently transient with every calendar year. However, the immense joy in seeing the professional and personal development of my students is what motivates me to keep working on my craft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mindset can lead to discussions with students that extend beyond the classroom and focus on life after school/university. Despite the countless number of students that I have taught or even spoken to after delivering a speech, there are common patterns that have emerged in the questions that are asked, with the most common question being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What career should I choose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a big question and an even bigger one to answer.&lt;br /&gt;
My first piece of advice is to “never listen to anyone’s advice”. Inherently, all advice is somewhat biased by personal experience and may not translate to another situation. Those of you that are perceptive, however, will realise that this piece of advice is a trap in itself, because by following this mantra, you are in fact breaking it. What I hope students take from this is to listen to everyone (especially those that care the most about you), but ultimately, back yourself and your decisions. If you make a mistake, good! Fail early, fail often and fail forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that being said, the next thing I say is to realise that passions are developed through hard work - they are not instantaneously created. If you are passionate about something now, there is a high likelihood that you practiced a skill that is integral to that passion, even if you are unaware of that skill as being important. For example, whilst I am passionate about teaching, I believe that it is the years and years of public speaking practice that I did as a child, which sparked this passion. My mum would make me rehearse speeches over and over and over until they were memorised word for word. Then she taught me how to project my voice. Then she taught me how to use hand gestures to engage an audience. The list goes on and on. I was forcibly entered into every public speaking competition in primary school that was available and the process of winning a few of those competitions created the building blocks for passion. When I was in high school, I put myself in positions to continually practice this skill by speaking at assemblies and working hard on the yearly English speeches. In university, I worked on campus as a radio presenter, then started doing stand up comedy, which then led to other public speaking events and finally, teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing to note here is that I have taken this mindset towards all aspects of my life, which is why I am such a big advocate for developing a strong work ethic over following your passion, because passion follows work ethic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give you one final example. When I was in Year 8 I remember that on my yearly report card I received a “D” for science. The only grade lower than this was an “E” which was reserved for students who either did not attend school or did not hand in any assessment tasks. I distinctly remember saying to myself “I can’t wait until I am in Year 11 and I can drop science!” Fast forward the clock to Year 10 subject selections and parental pressure ensured that I did Biology and Chemistry. I was adamant on dropping Biology, however, as this clashed with my favourite subject, Drama. My previous work ethic for developing my public speaking skills had already provided me with an aptitude for Drama classes. As a result, I had meeting after meeting with the Deputy Principal to try and balance my schedule to do both. I could not. Reluctantly, I chose Biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than being upset with this decision, I instead focused my energy on doing the best I could at Biology. My Year 11 report card shows the difficulty I experienced when all of my hard work on the subject led to a disheartening mark of 56%. I proceeded to work and work and work on the subject. Fast forward again to the end of year 12 and after years of practice, my final report card mark for Biology was 77%. It wasn’t amazing but it was progress and I was even starting to find Biology interesting. I also realised through this process that hard work was the answer to passion development. I ended up picking science in university and obtained a distinction average for my degree and published 2 papers in scientific journals whilst I was an undergraduate student. I became a science teacher, where I taught students the same subject that I was weakest at in high school. My hard work turned an undesirable course into a passion, which led me to where I am now, a PhD Candidate in Neuroscience at the Australian National University in Canberra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are there other career paths out there for me that I would be better suited for? It is not only possible, but it is in fact highly likely. Whilst I am extremely passionate about teaching, research has always been an avenue for me to develop my skills and become a better teacher (i.e. the more I know, the more I can help my students). In saying that, I started my PhD this year and I am putting in 60-70 hour workweeks. Multiply that across 4 years and I am very confident that I will be an extremely passionate researcher by the end of this process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t necessarily have to be able to see the bigger picture, in order to be able to start working towards it. Pick a direction, set goals, work hard, and personal progress will allow for opportunities to develop. Don’t follow your passions, foster them with a strong work ethic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First behavioural characterisation of a knockout mouse model for the transforming growth factor (TGF)-β superfamily cytokine, MIC-1/GDF15</title>
      <link>/publication/20170112_mic-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/20170112_mic-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macrophage inhibitory cytokine-1 (MIC-1), also known as growth differentiation factor 15 (GDF15), is a stress response cytokine. MIC-1/GDF15 is secreted into the cerebrospinal fluid and increased levels of MIC-1/GDF15 are associated with a variety of diseases including cognitive decline. Furthermore, Mic-1/Gdf15 knockout mice (Mic-1 KO) weigh more, have increased adiposity, associated with increased spontaneous food intake, and exhibit reduced basal energy expenditure and physical activity. The current study was designed to comprehensively determine the role of MIC-1/GDF15 on behavioural domains of male and female knockout mice including locomotion, exploration, anxiety, cognition, social behaviours, and sensorimotor gating. Mic-1 KO mice exhibited a task-dependent increase in locomotion and exploration and reduced anxiety-related behaviours across tests. Spatial working memory and social behaviours were not affected by Mic-1/Gdf15 deficiency. Interestingly, knockout mice formed an increased association with the conditioned stimulus in fear conditioning testing and also displayed significantly improved prepulse inhibition. Overall sex effects were evident for social behaviours, fear conditioning, and sensorimotor gating. This is the first study defining the role of Mic-1/Gdf15 in a number of behavioural domains. Whether the observed impact is based on direct actions of Mic-1/Gdf15 deficiency on the CNS or whether the behavioural effects are mediated by indirect actions on e.g. other neurotransmitter systems must be clarified in future studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Low, J. K., &lt;strong&gt;Ambikairajah, A.&lt;/strong&gt;, Shang, K., Brown, D. A., Tsai, V. W., Breit, S. N., &amp;amp; Karl, T. (2017). First behavioural characterisation of a knockout mouse model for the transforming growth factor (TGF)-β superfamily cytokine, MIC-1/GDF15. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;PloS one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 12(1): e0168416. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0168416&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0168416&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>External Project</title>
      <link>/project/external-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/external-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internal Project</title>
      <link>/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A visual MRI atrophy rating scale for the amyotrophic lateral sclerosis-frontotemporal dementia continuum</title>
      <link>/publication/20140218_als-ftd-rating-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/20140218_als-ftd-rating-scale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our objective was to distinguish ALS, ALS-FTD and bvFTD via a novel visual MRI cortical atrophy scale that can be employed in a clinical setting. MRI images of 100 participants (33 ALS, 11 ALS-FTD, 22 bvFTD and 34 controls) were rated in four brain areas: orbitofrontal cortex, anterior temporal pole, anterior cingulate, and motor cortex. Areas were rated on a 5- point Likert scale by two raters blinded to the diagnosis. Results demonstrated that bvFTD patients showed the highest levels of atrophy across all regions, while ALS patients had the lowest atrophy scores. ALS-FTD patients have higher atrophy ratings compared to ALS patients for the motor cortex, anterior cingulate and anterior temporal lobe, with a statistical trend for the orbitofrontal cortex. ALS-FTD patients were not significantly different from bvFTD for any of the brain regions. These findings were confirmed in a post hoc VBM analysis of the same participants. Our study demonstrates that a simple visual MRI rating scale can reliably distinguish ALS, ALS-FTD and bvFTD atrophy patterns in a clinical setting. Motor cortex, anterior cingulate and anterior temporal atrophy emerged as good diagnostic markers for ALS-FTD. Employment of this MRI rating scale can complement clinical diagnostics of patients in the ALS-FTD continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ambikairajah, A.,&lt;/strong&gt; Devenney, E., Flanagan, E., Yew, B., Mioshi, E., Kiernan, M. C., Hodges, J. R., &amp;amp; Hornberger, M. (2014). A visual MRI atrophy rating scale for the amyotrophic lateral sclerosis-frontotemporal dementia continuum. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis and Frontotemporal Degeneration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 15(3-4), 226-234. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3109/21678421.2014.880180&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;doi:10.&lt;sup&gt;3109&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;21678421&lt;/sub&gt;.2014.880180&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work ethic</title>
      <link>/post/180809-work-ethic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/180809-work-ethic/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;goals.jpg&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;August marks my 6-month milestone since commencing a PhD program. As a result of this significant milestone, I thought I would use this week’s blog post to reflect on the journey so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I think about what skill has helped me get to this point, two words immediately spring to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work ethic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student you are largely in control of your own schedule and you can direct your own hours. This can be empowering for some but overwhelming for others. It is very easy to keep preoccupied with “productive procrastination”, which essentially means working on tasks that feel like work, but are really distractions or low priority items that direct your focus away from your main goal i.e. me writing this blog post is a perfect example of a productive procrastination task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In saying this, however, I have found that the autonomy of a PhD schedule suits me well as I can still engage in activities that I am passionate about, such as teaching and science communication. As long as the work gets done, my “work time activities” are never questioned. In fact, I took two hours off work earlier in the week to go to the gym…but I will come back to this in a second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidently, a strong work ethic is a key skill to develop when learning how to thrive in a highly autonomous environment. The question then becomes, how does one develop a work ethic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few key things that have helped me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a focus/vision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understand what you want and more importantly WHY you want it. If you are not sure what you want, don’t worry. Focus on the next few tips instead, as your vision can be shaped over time with experience. The most important thing right now is that you pick a direction (any direction!) and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn the core principles of goal setting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goal setting is the tool, which can help you bridge the gap between the unattainable and the attainable. Most people who start writing down their goals usually aim for things that are either too general, irrelevant to their main focus, too difficult or some combination of the above. I am definitely guilty of this as evident by a guitar that has been sitting in my room, which has hardly been touched for the past 3 years. Therefore it is important to note that goal setting is a skill in itself, which you become better at utilising and implementing with continual practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn that failing can be fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you shift your mindset to start viewing failures as an opportunity to continually learn and develop, it can help shape a positive perspective on difficult goals. This can be easier said then done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was doing stand up comedy regularly, I had an opportunity to get to know Australian Comedian Sammy J. His advice for me was to try new things and enjoy the early days because that is when you could fail over and over with hardly anyone watching. I soon realised that the reason why it is difficult to develop a positive relationship with failure is because there are usually consequences associated with failing, which become bigger as your notability and levels of responsibility increases. It is important to note, however, that the path to developing discipline is inherently difficult and filled with failure. Acknowledging this and integrating a positive perspective about failure into your foundation can be key to learning how to deal with the consequences of failing at any level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t be too tough on yourself when you don’t achieve a goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a lesson that I am still learning and working on. I have found that in some situations, it can be good to scale back goals, however, in other situations, the goals that you fail forward on multiple times can set you up for a euphoric feeling of success. Once again, understanding this balance comes with practice (notice a common theme here?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward yourself when you achieve a goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger I had extreme difficulty with focusing, especially when it came to reading. Whilst this was a weakness that I could get away with in high school (thank you SparkNotes…), the demands of university quickly exposed this. As a result, I would set small goals and reward myself for achieving those goals. This involved sitting down to read one page of a book. After several sittings, I would increase the threshold to 2 pages, then 3, then 4, and so on and so forth. Each time I achieved this goal I rewarded myself with something I enjoyed. To this day, I still do this. I mentioned that I took a few hours to go to the gym earlier in the week. Exercise has become a luxury in my current life and I used it as a reward after I had completed an extremely arduous task for my PhD. In saying that, I also find that it is useful to penalise myself when a goal is not met. This gives more weight and meaning when a goal is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show me your friends and I’ll show you your future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love this quote, mostly because it emphasises that your environment can strongly influence your behaviours. Why is this relevant to developing a strong work ethic? Well, if you are the hardest working person in the room, then you are probably in the wrong room. Surround yourself with people that have qualities you admire and at the very least, you can observe what a life is like when those qualities are practiced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, there are a number of ways that a work ethic can be fostered and developed, but I hope that this article provides a useful perspective on some tools that can help. In saying this, I know that there can be a lot of confusion when it comes to developing a strong work ethic, so a core message that I want to leave this article with is that people are commended in public for the hours and hours of practice that they do in private. At the end of the day, it’s all about practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
