<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ananthan Ambikairajah</title>
    <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ananthan Ambikairajah</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Anxiety in academia?</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/190607-anxiety-in-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/190607-anxiety-in-academia/</guid>
      <description>A career in academia is stressful. There are constant pressures to “publish or perish”, find sources of funding to sustain your work and complete a never-ending workload that, more often than not, tends to extend beyond the five day work week. The environment is highly competitive and often requires a willingness to be flexible, continually upskill and strategically plan ahead. These pressures exist when things are going well. Politics within academia can also add a layer of complexity to an already demanding profession.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plagiarism - what does it mean?</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/190508-self-plagiarism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/190508-self-plagiarism/</guid>
      <description>I have always thought that plagiarism was a relatively easy concept to understand. In short, if you copied someone else’s work or ideas without sufficient credit, then you were likely to be guilty of plagiarism. It wasn’t until I entered academia that I began to question the meaning of plagiarism. Particularly the idea of self-plagiarism.
How can you plagiarise yourself?
One clear example in academia is to publish the exact same paper in two (or more) different journals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sci-Hub: A response to the scientific paywall</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180907-sci-hub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180907-sci-hub/</guid>
      <description>Being involved in science enables the development of critical thinking skills, which ultimately helps you view the world through a different lens. The most powerful way to achieve this perspective is by questioning one step further using a simple word – “why?”
For example, one question that has always puzzled me has been the commercialisation of water – Why do people pay for bottle water? Given that Australia’s water treatment process is of a high standard, I find it difficult to justify the cost of a resource that is readily available via tap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women in science - what responsibility do male scientists have?</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180817-women-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180817-women-in-science/</guid>
      <description>National Science Week is drawing to a close and last night I had the pleasure of watching Professor Veena Sahajwalla from the University of New South Wales (UNSW), Sydney and Dr Karl Kruszelnicki from the University of Sydney (USyd), give extremely passionate and engaging talks at the National Convention Centre in Canberra. Topics were diverse and ranged from explaining current and future electronic waste recycling strategies to discussing the importance of understanding why diet alcoholic drinks get you drunk quicker.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work ethic</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180809-work-ethic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180809-work-ethic/</guid>
      <description>August marks my 6-month milestone since commencing a PhD program. As a result of this significant milestone, I thought I would use this week’s blog post to reflect on the journey so far.
When I think about what skill has helped me get to this point, two words immediately spring to mind.
Work ethic.
As a PhD student you are largely in control of your own schedule and you can direct your own hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should scientists engage with the public?</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180803-science-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180803-science-communication/</guid>
      <description>Words are incredible. Words can be used to express ideas, comfort others, inspire movements to spark change, create music that can unite people from different cultures…the list goes on. Equally so, however, words can be used to spread misinformation, cause confusion that leads to conflict and distrust, especially when taken out of context.
You may be wondering why I am talking about words when the title of this article is about scientists and public engagement?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t follow your passions. Foster them</title>
      <link>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180727-dont-follow-your-passions-foster-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananthanambikairajah.com/post/180727-dont-follow-your-passions-foster-them/</guid>
      <description>When I teach students, I take the same level of responsibility, care and commitment towards their learning and development as I would hope another teacher would show my future children. This can, at times, be emotionally arduous, when such a heavy investment is put into relationships that are inherently transient with every calendar year. However, the immense joy in seeing the professional and personal development of my students is what motivates me to keep working on my craft.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>